Deniz Mevlevioglu

PhD Candidate

LinkedIn Profile: <u>linkedin.com/in/deniz-mevlevioglu</u>

Website: <u>denizmev.com</u>

dmevlevioglu@gmail.com | +353 85 2333655

Profile

I'm a Computer Science PhD candidate at University College Cork, researching real-time anxiety classification in Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy. My research interests include onbody physiological sensors, machine learning, and virtual reality. Experienced tutor and demonstrator for varying topics in Computer Science, such as web development, authoring and 3D modelling.

Skills

- Academic Research
- Software Development
- Game Development
- Teaching
- · Web Development

Programming Languages

- C#
- Python
- Java
- JS

Interests

- Human-Computer Interaction
- Virtual Reality
- Smart Health
- Biosensors
- Machine Learning

Languages

- English (Full Professional Proficiency)
- Turkish (Native)

Technologies

- Keras
- TensorFlow
- SKLearn
- Pytorch
- SPSS

- Unity
- Blender
- Three.is
- Git
- Linux

Publications

Real-time Classification of Anxiety in Virtual Reality Therapy Using Biosensors and a Convolutional Neural Network.

Deniz Mevlevioğlu, Sabin Tabirca, and David Murphy. 2024.

MDPI Biosensors 14 (3)

DOI: 10.3390/bios14030131

Anxiety Classification in Virtual Reality Using Biosensors: A Mini Scoping Review.

Deniz Mevlevioğlu, Sabin Tabirca, and David Murphy. 2023.

PLoS One 18 (7)

DOI: <u>10.1371/journal.pone.0287984</u>

Emotional Virtual Reality Stroop Task

Deniz Mevlevioğlu, Sabin Tabirca, and David Murphy. 2023.

IEEE International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications

Workshops and other Affiliated Events (PerCom Workshops)

DOI: 10.1109/PerComWorkshops56833.2023.10150350

Emotional Virtual Reality Stroop Task: an Immersive Cognitive Test

Deniz Mevlevioğlu, Sabin Tabirca, and David Murphy. 2022.

In Proceedings of the ACM International Conference on Interactive Media Experiences (IMX '22).

DOI: <u>10.1145/3505284.3532988</u>

Real-time Anxiety Prediction in Virtual Reality Therapy.

Deniz Mevlevioğlu, Sabin Tabirca, and David Murphy. 2021.

Proceedings of the 12th ACM Multimedia Systems Conference (MMSys '22).

DOI: 10.1145/3524273.3533926

Emotional Virtual Reality Stroop Task: Pilot Design.

Deniz Mevlevioğlu, Sabin Tabirca, and David Murphy. 2021.

In Proceedings of the 27th ACM Symposium on Virtual Reality Software and Technology (VRST '21).

DOI: <u>10.1145/3489849.3489952</u>

Visual Respiratory Feedback in Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy: A Pilot Study.

Deniz Mevlevioğlu, Sabin Tabirca, and David Murphy. 2021.

In Proceedings of the ACM International Conference on Interactive Media Experiences (IMX '21).

DOI: <u>10.1145/3452918.3458799</u>

Real-time Anxiety Prediction in Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy.

Deniz Mevlevioğlu, David Murphy, and Sabin Tabirca. 2021. In Adjunct Proceedings of the ACM International Conference on Interactive Media Experiences (IMX '21).

DOI: <u>10.6084/m9.figshare.14699751.v1</u>

Education



PhD in Computer Science

University College Cork

2020 - 2024

• Thesis Title: "Real-time Anxiety Classification in Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy"



Msc In Interactive Media (Computer Science)

University College Cork

2018 - 2019

- Thesis Title: "Visual Respiratory Feedback in Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy"
- 1:1 Honours



BA in Psychology

BAU Bahcesehir University

2018 - 2019

• 74/100 GPA

Other Education



Epigeum Research Integrity

Oxford University Press 2020



Pedagogical Formation

Marmara University 2018

Work Experience



Demonstrator

University College Cork, School of Computer Science and Information Technology September 2019 to Present

Responsibilities:

- Demonstrated for practical sessions to a class of approximately 40 MSc students
- Presented over five tutorials per semester on computer science topics
- Guided students through problem-solving to improve their programming skills Skills and technologies:

 $\label{eq:cssol} \textit{Virtual Reality} \bullet \textit{Python} \bullet \textit{Java} \bullet \textit{HTML} \bullet \textit{CSS} \bullet \textit{JavaScript} \bullet \textit{PHP} \bullet \textit{Blender} \bullet \textit{jQuery} \bullet \textit{three.js} \bullet \textit{WebGL} \bullet \textit{Teaching}$



Visiting Researcher

University of Virginia, Link Lab June 2023 to September 2023

Responsibilities:

- Designed and carried out the research project entitled "Interpersonal synchrony of socially anxious dyads during Zoom video calls".
- Made presentations about my research to the team
- Collaborated with a team of psychologists and engineers

Skills and technologies:

Python • Biosensors • R • Project Management • Collaboration



Tutor

University College Cork, Munster Programming Training June 2019 to June 2023

Responsibilities:

- Delivered lectures that enabled over 60 secondary students to be proficient in creating the front-end and back-end of their personal websites from scratch
- Provided hands-on exercises each week based on the students' levels
- Created and graded assignments

Skills and technologies:

HTML • CSS • JavaScript • PHP • SQL • MySQL • Apache • Teaching • Communication

Web Developer

Freelance

June 2019 to October 2020

Responsibilities:

- Designed and developed personal and e-commerce websites
- Came up with dynamic solutions based on customer needs
- Worked with a team of designers and developers
- Made sure the websites follow accessibility standards
- Provided SEO

Skills and technologies:

HTML • CSS • JavaScript • PHP • WordPress • SEO • Development



Tutor

University College Cork, School of Arts and Humanities June 2019 to June 2023

Responsibilities:

- Prepared and delivered tutorials to a class of 40 BA students about creating a personal website using WordPress
- Created hands-on exercises to analyse their skills and needs
- Introduced and familiarised students with technologies useful for academia Skills and technologies:

Teaching • HTML • CSS • WordPress • Communication



Intern School Counselor

Feridun Tumer Technical Anatolian Secondary School January 2017 to June 2017

Responsibilities:

- Made a year-long education plan after assessing student needs
- Held introductory seminars to students and employees, providing information about counselling
- Created individualised education programs for students with special needs Skills and technologies:

Teaching • Counselling • Communication

Activities



Guest Lecturer

University College Cork, School of Computer Science and Information Technology 2022-2023

 Prepared and delivered a guest lecture with the topic "Using Python for Scripting in Blender" to approximately forty postgraduate students



Ireland Team Lead

European Girls' Olympiads of Informatics 2022

 Represented the Irish Team in the European Girls' Olympiad in Informatics as a team lead. Our team came back with a bronze medal.



Project Advisor

University College Cork, School of Computer Science and Information Technology 2022

 Supervised two Master's projects in the field of Computer Science, Human-Computer Interaction and Virtual Reality



Student Volunteer Chair

ACM International Conference on Interactive Media Experiences (IMX) 2022

 Directed and monitored a team of student volunteers to aid hundreds of participants for ACM IMX 2022, the leading international conference for interactive media experiences held in Aveiro, Portugal and virtually



Academic Speaker

NBT Berlin - International Forum on Neural Engineering & Brain Technologies 2022

 Presented my work titled 'Real-time anxiety prediction in Virtual Reality' to more than a hundred people in Berlin



Panellist

SFI Advance CRT Research Colloquium 2022

 Organised and presented student contributions in the SFI ADVANCE research colloquium held in Dublin



Competitor - Team XHalers

VR4Rehab Competition

2021

 Collaborated with a team of physiotherapists, nurses, physicians and computer scientists to design and prototype "Short games for long covid"; a VR application for aiding in the management of long-covid symptoms for the VR4Rehab hackathon by Interreg, held virtually

Projects

Emotional Virtual Reality Stroop Task (eVRST)

An emotional Virtual Reality variant of the well-established cognitive test Stroop Colour-Word Task.

Technologies:

Unity • C# • Shimmer GSR • Myndplay Myndband • GIMP • Audacity

Visual Respiratory Feedback in Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy

An experience that lets the user experience height in the comfort of VR, incorporating physiological signals and respiratory biofeedback.

Technologies:

Unity • C# • Shimmer • Myndplay • Reaper

Real-time Anxiety Classification in Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy

A decision-support system in VR therapy that uses heart rate, skin conductance and brain activity for seamless, objective feedback.

Technologies:

Unity • C# • Shimmer GSR • Myndplay Myndband • GIMP • Audacity

Discord LLM Chatbots

Two chatbots that are capable of processing text and responding in a meaningful way. "Llan" is programmed using the discord.js library and GPT-3 API. It is good at answering general questions and creative tasks such as making ASCII art and writing poems. The second one, "Denizbot", is programmed using pycord library and GPT-J models. It

is fine-tuned using LORA to speak similarly to its creator, me.

Technologies:

JS • Python • GPT-3 • GPT-J • node.js • discord.js • pycord

00000

A short and fun game where you play as a small ball rolling around and getting bigger by consuming enemies smaller in size and shooting enemies bigger in size.

Technologies:

Unity • C# • Shimmer GSR • Myndplay Myndband • GIMP • Audacity